<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-wkumari-dhc-capport-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!--c WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="DHCP Captive-Portal">Captive-Portal identification in
    DHCP</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Olafur Gudmundsson" initials="O." surname="Gudmundsson">
      <organization>Shinkuro Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4922 Fairmont Av, Suite 250</street>

          <city>Bethesda</city>

          <region>MD</region>

          <code>20814</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ogud@ogud.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paul Ebersman" initials="P." surname="Ebersman">
      <organization>Infoblox</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ebersman-ietf@dragon.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Steve Sheng" initials="S." surname="Sheng">
      <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
      Numbers</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>

          <country>United States of America</country>

          <code>90094</code>

          <city>Los Angeles</city>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1.310.301.5800</phone>

        <email>steve.sheng@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="23" month="January" year="2014" />

    <area>template</area>

    <workgroup>DHC</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>In many environments (such as hotels, coffee shops and other
      establishments that offer Internet service to customers), it is common
      to start new connections in a captive portal mode, i.e. highly restrict
      what the customer can do until the customer has accepted terms of
      service, provided payment information or authenticated.</t>

      <t>This document describes a DHCP option to inform clients that they are
      behind some sort of captive portal device, and that they will need to
      authenticate to get Internet Access.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In many environments (coffee shops and hotels), users need to connect
      to a captive portal device and agree to an acceptable use policy or
      provide billing information before they can access the Internet.</t>

      <t>In order to present the user with the captive portal web page, many
      devices perform DNS and / or HTTP and / or IP hijacks. As well as being
      kludgy hacks, these techniques looks very similar to attacks that DNSSEC
      and TLS protect against.</t>

      <t>This document describes a DHCP option (Captive-Portal) that informs
      DHCP clients that they are behind a captive portal device, and how to
      contact it.</t>

      <t>This document neither condones nor condemns captive portals; instead
      it recognises that they are here to stay, and attempts to improve the
      user's experience.</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Background">
      <t>Many Internet Service Providers (ISPs) that offer public Internet
      access require the user to first accept an Acceptable Use Policy (AUP)
      and / or provides billing information (such as their last name and / or
      room number in a hotel, credit card information, etc) through a web
      interface.</t>

      <t>In order to meet this requirement, some ISPs implement a captive
      portal (CP) - a system that intercepts user requests and redirects them
      to an interstitial login page.</t>

      <t>Captive portals intercept and redirects user requests in a number of
      ways, including:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>DNS Redirection</t>

          <t>IP Redirection</t>

          <t>HTTP Redirection</t>

          <t>Restricted scope addresses</t>

          <t>Traffic blocking (until the user is authenticated)</t>
        </list>In order to ensure that the user is unable to access the
      Internet, captive portals usually implement IP based filters, or place
      the user in to a restricted VLAN or restricted IP range until after they
      have been authorized.</t>

      <section title="DNS Redirection">
        <t>The CP either intercepts all DNS traffic or advertises itself (for
        example using DHCP) as the recursive server for the network. Until the
        user has authenticated to the captive portal, the CP responds to all
        DNS requests listing the address of its web portal. Once the user has
        authenticated the CP returns the "correct" addresses.</t>

        <t>This technique has many shortcomings. It fails if the client is
        performing DNSSEC validation, or if the client already has the DNS
        information cached.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="HTTP Redirection">
        <t>In this implementation, the CP acts like a transparent HTTP proxy;
        but when it sees an HTTP request from an unauthenticated client, it
        intercepts the request and responds with an HTTP status code 302 to
        redirect the client to the Captive Portal Login.</t>

        <t>The issues with this technique include:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>It fails if the user is only using HTTPS</t>

            <t>It exposes various private user information, such as HTTP
            Cookies, etc.</t>

            <t>It doesn't work if the client has a VPN and / or proxies their
            web traffic to an external web proxy.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="IP Hijacking">
        <t>In this scenario, the captive portal intercepts connections to any
        IP address. It spoofs the destination IP address and "pretends" to be
        whatever the user tried to access.</t>

        <t>This technique has similar issues as the HTTP solution, but may
        also break other protocols, and may expose more of the users private
        information, etc.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The Captive-Portal DHCP Option">
      <t>The Captive Portal DHCP Option (TBA1) informs the DHCP client that it
      is behind a captive portal and provides the URI to access the
      authentication page. This is primarily intended to improve the user
      experiance; for the forseeable future captive portals will still need to
      implement the interception techniques to serve legacy clinets.</t>

      <t>This draft is not intended to provide guidance on how to implement a
      captive portal. As such, it assumes that the captive portal on a
      dual-stack or IPv6-only network is already capable of intercepting IPv6
      traffic. However, in order to support IPv6 with the proposed DHCP
      option, there are some additional considerations. In a dual-stack
      network, the network supports both IPv4 and IPv6 protocols
      simultaneously, but can have a mix of IPv4-only, IPv6-only, and
      dual-stack devices using the network, meaning that it may be necessary
      to have parallel notifications via DHCPv4 and DHCPv6.</t>

      <t>IPv4-only and dual-stack devices can technically both support
      receiving the option via DHCPv4, but dual-stack implementations would
      need to ensure that the correct action would be taken for both IPv4 and
      IPv6 traffic despite only receiving an option via IPv4. For
      devices/networks that only speak IPv6, and to avoid this dependency on
      the implementation, a DHCPv6 option is necessary. </t>

      <t>[ED NOTE:] This is complicated by the fact that not all devices
      support DHCPv6, and thus it may be necessary to investigate other
      methods to notify IPv6-only devices of a captive portal. Since this
      option is only intended to help clients gracefully deal with networks
      that have a captive portal, it may be acceptable to note that if a
      client does not support DHCPv6, it simply won&rsquo;t be able to take
      advantage of this optimization, but will otherwise function normally.
      [/note]</t>

      <t>The format of the DHCP Captive-Portal DHCP option is identical for
      both DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 and is shown below.<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[  Code    Len          Data
  +------+------+------+------+------+--   --+-----+
  | code |  len |  URI                  ...        |
  +------+------+------+------+------+--   --+-----+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Code: The Captive-Portal DHCP Option (TBA1 for DHCPv4, TBA2 for
          DHCPv6)</t>

          <t>Len: The length, in octets of the URI.</t>

          <t>URI: The URI of the authentication page that the user should
          connect to.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The URI MUST be a URL with an IP-literal for the host portion (to
      remove the need to allow DNS from unauthenticated clients). The DHCPv4
      URI MUST contain an IPv4 address, and the DHCPv6 URI MUST contain an
      IPv6 address (to account for IPv4 only or IPv6 only capable devices -
      not everyting is dual stack!)</t>

      <t>[ED NOTE: Using an address literal is less than ideal, but better
      than the alternatives. Recommending a DNS name means that the CP would
      need to allow DNS from unauthenticated clients (as we don't want to
      force users to use the CP's provided DNS) and some folk would use this
      to DNS Tunnel out. This would make the CP admin block external
      recursives).]</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Use of the Captive-Portal Option">
      <t>[ED NOTE: This section is, and probably will remain, fairly hand
      wavy. This option provides notice to the OS / User applications that
      there is a CP, but I think that the UI / etc is best designed / handled
      by the Operating System vendors / Application developers. ]</t>

      <t>The purpose of the Captive-Portal DHCP Option is to inform the
      operating system and applications that they are behind a captive portal
      type device and will need to authenticate before getting network access
      (and how to reach the authentication page).</t>

      <t>The exact method that the interaction with the user occurs is device
      / operating system / application dependent. The below is simply one
      option.</t>

      <t>When the device receives a DHCP response with the Captive-Portal
      Option it SHOULD:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Not initiate new IP connections until the CP has been satisfied.
          [TODO(Someone): Existing connections should be quiesced. This will
          happen more often than some expect -- you buy 1h of Internet at a
          cafe and stay there for 3h -- this will "interrupt" you a few
          times).]</t>

          <t>Present a dialog box to the user informing that they are behind a
          captive portal and ask if they wish to proceed.</t>

          <t>If the user elects to proceed, the device should initiate a
          connection to the captive portal login page using a web browser
          configured with a separate cookie store. Some captive portals send
          the user a cookie when they authenticate (so that the user can
          re-authenticate more easily in the future - the browser should keep
          these CP cookies separate from other cookies.</t>

          <t>Once the user has authenticated (how does it know? HTTP
          response?! Probe (ugh?)) normal IP connectivity should resume.</t>

          <t>The device should (using an OS dependent method) expose to the
          user / user applications that they have connected though a captive
          portal (for example by creating a file in /proc/net/ containing the
          interface and captive portal URI). This should continue until the
          network changes, or a new DHCP message without the CP is
          received.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[ This section stolen from draft-ietf-dhc-access-network-identifier.
      :-) ]</t>

      <t>This document defines DHCPv4 Captive-Portal option which requires
      assignment of DHCPv4 option code TBA1 assigned from "Bootp and DHCP
      options" registry (http://www.iana.org/assignments/
      bootp-dhcp-parameters/bootp-dhcp-parameters.xml), as specified in
      [RFC2939].</t>

      <t>The IANA is requested to assign an option codes for the DHCPv6
      Captive-Portal (TBA2) option from the "DHCPv6 and DHCPv6 options"
      registry (http://
      www.iana.org/assignments/dhcpv6-parameters/dhcpv6-parameters.xml).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>An attacker with the ability to inject DHCP messages could include
      this option and so force users to contact him. As an attacker with this
      capability could simply list himself as the default gateway (and so see
      all the victim's traffic), we do not think this gives them significantly
      more capabilities. Fake DHCP servers are currently a security concern -
      this doesn't make them any better or worse.</t>

      <t>Devices and systems that automatically connect to open network could
      potentially be tracked using the techniques described in this document
      (forcing the user to continually authenticate, or exposing their browser
      fingerprint), but similar tracking could already be performed with the
      standard captive portal mechanisms, so this doesn't seem to give the
      attackers more capabilities.</t>

      <t>By simplifying the interaction with the captive portal systems, and
      doing away with the need for interception, we think that users will be
      less likely to disable useful security safeguards like DNSSEC
      validation, VPNs, etc.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The primary author has discussed this idea with a number of folk, and
      asked them to assist by becoming co-authors. Unfortunately he has
      forgotten who many of them were; if you were one of them, I
      apologize.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Vint Cerf for the initial idea / asking me to write this.
      Thanks to Wes George for supplying the v6 text.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <reference anchor="IANA.AS_Numbers"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/as-numbers">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Autonomous System (AS) Numbers">Autonomous System
          (AS) Numbers</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-iana-objects-03.xml'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From -00 to -01:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Many nits and editorial changes.</t>

          <t>Whole bunch of extra text and review from Wes George on v6.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From initial to -00.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Nothing changed in the template!</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
