<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wkumari-dhc-capport-14" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!--c WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="DHCP Captive-Portal">Captive-Portal Identification in DHCP
    / RA</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Olafur Gudmundsson" initials="O." surname="Gudmundsson">
      <organization>CloudFlare</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>San Francisco</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94107</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>olafur@cloudflare.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paul Ebersman" initials="P." surname="Ebersman">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ebersman-ietf@dragon.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Steve Sheng" initials="S." surname="Sheng">
      <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
      Numbers</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>

          <country>United States of America</country>

          <code>90094</code>

          <city>Los Angeles</city>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1.310.301.5800</phone>

        <email>steve.sheng@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="18" month="June" year="2015"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>In many environments offering short-term or temporary Internet access
      (such as coffee shops), it is common to start new connections in a
      captive portal mode. This highly restricts what the customer can do
      until the customer has authenticated.</t>

      <t>This document describes a DHCP option (and a RA extension) to inform
      clients that they are behind some sort of captive portal device, and
      that they will need to authenticate to get Internet Access. It is not a
      full solution to address all of the issues that clients may have with
      captive portals; it is designed to be used in larger solutions.</t>

      <t>[ Ed note (remove): This document is being developed in github:
      https://github.com/wkumari/draft-wkumari-dhc-capport . ]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In many environments, users need to connect to a captive portal
      device and agree to an acceptable use policy (AUP) and / or provide
      billing information before they can access the Internet. It is
      anticipated that the IETF will work on a more fully featured protocol at
      some point, to ease interaction with Captive Portals. Regardless of how
      that protocol operates, it is expected that this document will provide
      needed functionality because the client will need to know when it is
      behind a CP and how to contact it.</t>

      <t>In order to present users with the payment or AUP pages, the captive
      portal device has to intercept the user's connections and redirect the
      user to the captive portal, using methods that are very similar to
      man-in-the-middle (MITM) attacks. As increasing focus is placed on
      security, and end nodes adopt a more secure stance, these interception
      techniques will become less effective and / or more intrusive.</t>

      <t>This document describe a DHCP (<xref target="RFC2131"/>) option
      (Captive Portal) and an IPv6 Router Advertisement (RA) (<xref
      target="RFC4861"/>) extension that informs clients that they are behind
      a captive portal device and how to contact it.</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The Captive-Portal Option">
      <t>The Captive Portal DHCP / RA Option informs the client that it is
      behind a captive portal and provides the URI to access an authentication
      page. This is primarily intended to improve the user experience by
      getting them to the captive portal faster; for the foreseeable future,
      captive portals will still need to implement the interception techniques
      to serve legacy clients, and clients will need to perform probing to
      detect captive portals.</t>

      <t>In order to support multiple "classes" of clients (e.g: IPv4 only,
      IPv6 only with DHCPv6(<xref target="RFC3315"/>), IPv6 only with RA) the
      captive portal can provide the URI via multiple methods (IPv4 DHCP, IPv6
      DHCP, IPv6 RA). The captive portal operator should ensure that the URIs
      handed out are equivalent to reduce the chance of operational
      problems.</t>

      <t>In order to avoid having to perform DNS interception, the URI SHOULD
      contain an address literal, but MAY contain a DNS name if the captive
      portal allows the client to perform DNS requests to resolve the
      name.</t>

      <section title="IPv4 DHCP Option">
        <t>The format of the IPv4 Captive-Portal DHCP option is shown
        below.<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  Code    Len          Data
  +------+------+------+------+------+--   --+-----+
  | code | len  |  URI                  ...        |
  +------+------+------+------+------+--   --+-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Code: The Captive-Portal DHCPv4 Option (TBA1) (one octet)</t>

            <t>Len: The length, in octets of the URI.</t>

            <t>URI: The URI of the authentication page that the user should
            connect to.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv6 DHCP Option">
        <t>The format of the IPv6 Captive-Portal DHCP option is shown below.
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |          option-code          |          option-len           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   .                      URI (variable length)                    .
   |                              ...                              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: The Captive-Portal DHCPv6Option (TBA2) (two
            octets)</t>

            <t>option-len: The length, in octets of the URI.</t>

            <t>URI: The URI of the authentication page that the user should
            connect to.</t>
          </list>See <xref target="RFC7227"/>, Section 5.7 for more examples
        of DHCP Options with URIs.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The Captive-Portal IPv6 RA Option">
      <t>This section describes the Captive-Portal Router Advertisement
      option.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |     Length    |              URI              .
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               .
   .                                                               .
   .                                                               .
   .                                                               .
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            Figure 2: Captive-Portal RA Option Format]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Type">TBA3</t>

          <t hangText="Length">8-bit unsigned integer. The length of the
          option (including the Type and Length fields) in units of 8
          bytes.</t>

          <t hangText="URI">The URI of the authentication page that the user
          should connect to. For the reasons described above, the implementer
          might want to use an IP address literal instead of a DNS name. This
          should be padded with NULL (0x0) to make the total option length
          (including the Type and Length fields) a multiple of 8 bytes.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines two DHCP Captive-Portal options, one for IPv6
      and one for IPv6. It requires assignment of an option code (TBA1) to be
      assigned from "Bootp and DHCP options" registry
      (http://www.iana.org/assignments/
      bootp-dhcp-parameters/bootp-dhcp-parameters.xml), as specified in
      [RFC2939]. It also requires assignment of an option code (TBA2) from the
      "DHCPv6 and DHCPv6 options" registry
      (http://www.iana.org/assignments/dhcpv6-parameters/dhcpv6-parameters.xml).</t>

      <t>IANA is also requested to assign an IPv6 RA Option Type code (TBA3)
      from the "IPv6 Neighbor Discovery Option Formats" registry. Thanks
      IANA!</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>An attacker with the ability to inject DHCP messages could include
      this option and so force users to contact an address of his choosing. As
      an attacker with this capability could simply list himself as the
      default gateway (and so intercept all the victim's traffic); this does
      not provide them with significantly more capabilities. Fake DHCP servers
      / fake RAs are currently a security concern - this doesn't make them any
      better or worse.</t>

      <t>Devices and systems that automatically connect to an open network
      could potentially be tracked using the techniques described in this
      document (forcing the user to continually authenticate, or exposing
      their browser fingerprint). However, similar tracking can already be
      performed with the standard captive portal mechanisms, so this technique
      does not give the attackers more capabilities.</t>

      <t>By simplifying the interaction with the captive portal systems, and
      doing away with the need for interception, we think that users will be
      less likely to disable useful security safeguards like DNSSEC
      validation, VPNs, etc. In addition, because the system knows that it is
      behind a captive portal, it can know not to send cookies, credentials,
      etc. Redirection to a portal where TLS can be used without hijacking can
      ameliorate some of the implications of connecting to a potentially
      malicious captive portal.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Vint Cerf for the initial idea / asking me to write this.
      Thanks to Wes George for supplying the IPv6 text. Thanks to Lorenzo and
      Erik for the V6 RA kick in the pants.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Fred Baker, Paul Hoffman, Ted Lemon, Martin Nilsson, Ole
      Troan and Asbjorn Tonnesen for detailed review and comments. Also great
      thanks to Joel Jaeggli for providing feedback and text.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3315'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7227'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2131'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'
?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From 13.2 to 13(posted):<list style="symbols">
          <t>Shortened the document by removing most of the [Editors notes],
          Section 2, Section 5 and Appendix A. They were mainly background and
          have served their purpose. This change suggested by Paul
          Hoffman.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 13.1 to 13.2:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Moved all of the "what an OS could do with this info" to an
          Appendix, to make it even clearer that this is simply an
          example.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -12 to -13.1:</t>

      <t>There was a Captive Portal Bar BoF held at the Dallas IETF meeting.
      See https://github.com/httpwg/wiki/wiki/Captive-Portals for some
      details. This document was discussed, and I got a fair bit of feedback.
      Incorporating some of this in -13.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>"In the text discussing why a captive portal notification might
          be useful (section 2.2 maybe?), perhaps you should say something
          about HSTS and HTTP2.0, since they will further erode the ability to
          use common captive portal redirection techniques." - Wes George.</t>

          <t>Integrated a bunch of useful comments from Martin Nilsson</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -11 to -12:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Integrated a whole bunch of comments from Ted Lemon, including
          missing references, track, missing size of DHCP option,</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 10 to 11:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Updated Olafur's affiliation.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 09 to 10:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Ted Lemon and Joel Jaeggli: there's no benefit to insisting on an
          ordering. I think you should just say that the ordering is
          indeterminate, and if different mechanisms give non-equivalent
          answers, this is likely to cause operational problems in
          practice.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 08 to 09:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Put back the DHCPv6 option, and made the fact that is separate
          from the DHCPv4 option clearer (Ted Lemon)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 07 to 08:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Incorporated comments from Ted Lemon. Made the document much
          shorter.</t>

          <t>Some cleanup.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 06 to 07:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Incoroprated a bunch of comments from Asbjorn Tonnesen</t>

          <t>Clarified that this document is only for the DHCP bits, not
          everything.</t>

          <t>CP's *can* do HTTP redirects to DNS names, as long as they allow
          access to all needed services.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 05 to 06:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Integrated comments from Joel, as below</t>

          <t>Better introduction text, around the "kludgy hacks" section.</t>

          <t>Better "neither condones nor condemns" text</t>

          <t>Fingerprint text.</t>

          <t>Some discussions on the v4 literal stuff.</t>

          <t>More Security Consideration text.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 04 to 05:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Integrated comments, primarily from Fred Baker.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From 03 to 04:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Some text cleanup for readability.</t>

          <t>Some disclaimers about it working better on initial connection
          versus CP timeout.</t>

          <t>Some more text explaining that CP interception is
          indistinguishable from an attack.</t>

          <t>Connectivity Check test.</t>

          <t>Posting just before the draft cutoff - &ldquo;I love deadlines. I
          love the whooshing noise they make as they go by.&rdquo; &mdash;
          Douglas Adams, The Salmon of Doubt</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -02 to 03:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Removed the DHCPv6 stuff (as suggested / requested by Erik
          Kline)</t>

          <t>Simplified / cleaned up text (I'm inclined to waffle on, then
          trim the fluff)</t>

          <t>This was written on a United flight with in-flight WiFi -
          unfortunately I couldn't use it because their CP was borked. :-P</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -01 to 02:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Added the IPv6 RA stuff.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -00 to -01:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Many nits and editorial changes.</t>

          <t>Whole bunch of extra text and review from Wes George on v6.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From initial to -00.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Nothing changed in the template!</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
